Guide to the Elaine Equi and Jerome Sala Papers MSS.204
Fales Library and Special Collections
Elaine Equi and Jerome Sala Papers
1972-2012
Fales Library and Special Collections
Equi, Elaine
Sala, Jerome
MSS.204
15 Linear Feet 22 manuscript boxes, 3 record cartons, 2 oversize flat boxes, one shared box
4 sound discs (cd) 4 commercial CDs
1 sound discs (lacquer) 1 45 RPM phonograph record
1 videocassettes (vhs)
650 Megabytes 1 CD-R
Elaine Equi and Jerome Sala are downtown poets who were active in Chicago's performance poetry scene. Both continue to write and publish their work. Elaine Equi teaches at New York University and in the Master of Fine Arts program at The New School. This collection contains correspondence with both Equi and Sala, poetry publications, audiovisual recordings of their works, and items from two recent exhibitions of Equi's work.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Elaine Equi in 2007.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in three series: Series I: Correspondence and Personal Papers; Series II: Published Works and Publications; Series III: Exhibitions.
Biographical Note
Poet Elaine Equi teaches at New York University and in the MFA Program at the New School. She has written more than ten books of poetry, including Sentences and Rain and Click and Clone: Poems. Born in Oak Park, Illinois, she received a BA and an MA in English from Columbia College, where she taught a poetry workshop for several years after graduating. Along with her husband, Jerome Sala, she was active in Chicago's performance poetry scene.
Jerome Sala is the author of seven poetry collections, including recent publications Corporations Are People Too! and The Cheapskates. A native of Chicago, he received his bachelor's degree from the University of Illinois at Chicago Circle. He and Equi later moved to New York where he received his doctorate in American Studies from New York University. He writes about cultural and media trends and criticism.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Fales Library with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, periodicals, poetry anthologies, self-published poems, exhibition guides, contracts, announcements, blog printouts, reviews, newsletters, interview transcripts, and oversize broadsides pertaining to Equi's and Sala's work from 1976 to 2012. It also contains their copies of their published works, CDs and a VHS tape recording of some of Equi's poems, and photographs from two later exhibits by Equi, "Votive Candy" and "A Guide to the Cinema Tarot."
Downtown Collection.; Poets, American -- 20th century.; Women poets, American.; Poets, American -- 20th century -- Correspondence.
- Series I: Correspondence and Personal Papers
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains correspondence, manuscripts and drafts, clippings and event brochures, contracts and agreements, photographs of Equi and Sala, and a manuscript of Sala's doctoral dissertation for New York University. Among the correspondence are letters from poets John Ashbery and David Trinidad and from Alice Quinn, poetry editor at The New Yorker.
  - Correspondence, catalogs, early scrapbook, photos, newsletters, unpublished article, 1979-2006 (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts, new work, unpublished articles, clippings, photographs, press releases, Jerome Sala's "The Great Rematch", 1981-2007 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, email printouts, birthday cards; conference, poetry reading, and event brochures and materials; contracts and agreements., 1992-1997, 2002-2012 (Box 3)
  - Draft of Jerome Sala's poetry dissertation for NYU American Studies Department, 2007 (Box 4)
- Series II: Published Works and Publications
  This series contains poetry anthologies and journals, exhibition catalogs, newsletters, magazines, and recordings of Equi's works. Included are copies of Equi's and Sala's published books, as well as publications edited by or containing works by Equi or Sala. This series also contains publications collected by Equi and Sala.
  - Includes Black & White, Greetings, Persephonic, Big Deal, Barney, Snap, Center, Stare, Temblor, Telephone, 1975-2001 (Box 5)
  - Includes cuz, Privates, Long News in the Short Century, Walk on the Wild Side, 1975-2003 (Box 6)
  - Includes Parnassus, Ploughshares, Whatever, Another Chicago Magazine, On the Bus, 1976-1999 (Box 7)
  - Includes Robert Zandvliet's the Varick Series, Praxis, Cover, Volt, Gas, Big Allis, Hair Trigger, 1977-2000 (Box 8)
  - Includes lacanian ink, Christy's Alpine Inn, OYEZ Revies, Juice, Brooklyn Review, Under 35, Paterns/Context/Time, 1977-2004 (Box 9)
  - Includes Skanky Possum, Virgin Mule, The World, b city, Diana's Fourth Almanac, Oink, 1977-2004 (Box 10)
  - Includes Central Park, Poetry International, banyan press ANTHOLOGY, Oulipo, Greetings, Mirage, Court Green, Bowery Women Poems, 1977-2007 (Box 11)
  - Includes Stare, Gnosis, Journal, Buhl Collection, 1979-2006 (Box 12)
  - Includes Poetry Project (edited by JS), Pome, Courier #1, Surface Tension, Paper Air, 1979-2007 (Box 13)
  - Includes Black Maria, b city, Helicopters over the Pyramids, Naming the Daytime Moon, Mississippi Review, Graffiti, the Tiny, 1980-2006 (Box 14)
  - Includes Gertrude Stein Awards, Coming Attractions, Saints of Hysteria, Conjunctions, Poet's Bookshelf, 1980-2007 (Box 15)
  - Includes Out of This World, Xcp, Chelsea, The American Voice, 1982-2003 (Box 16)
  - Includes Promethean, Sugar Mule, Forehead, Urbanus, Phoebe, 1987-2000 (Box 17)
  - Includes Little Caesar, Love Poems by Women, New American Writing, Will Work for Peace, 1990-2002 (Box 18)
  - Includes Aerial 9,Sulfur 27, Barrow Street; boundary 2, Caliban 14, Pressed Wafer, 1994-2005 (Box 19)
  - Includes Gargoyle, Insurance, Gulf Coast, Shiny, Blue Book Poetry, Diwan, Jack Spade, 1994-2007 (Box 20)
  - Includes This Full Green Hour, Why I Kick at Night, American Poets Against the War, Agriculture Reader, Griffin Poetry Prize Anthology, 2004-2009 (Box 21)
  - Includes Court Green, Visiting Wallace, Broome Street Review, Spectre, Blue Stranger with Mosaic Background, 2005-2012 (Box 22)
  - Includes Flagrant, Vanitas, Sometimes Things Seem Very Dark, 2007-2012 (Box 23)
  - Includes American Poetry Review, The Buhl Collection, Lit, In House, Ping Pong, Télérama, 2007-2012 (Box 24)
  - Printed works by Elaine Equi and Jerome Sala, 1978-2010 (Box 25)
  - Recorded works on CD, 1996-2004 (Box Shared Fales 015)
  - Video: Hanuman Presents!, 1999 (Box Shared Fales 015)
  - Includes Praxis 5, Inside Chicago, Spin, Poetry Flash, Spin, 1987-2007 (Box 26, Box Shared Fales 018)
- Series III: Exhibitions and Graphics
  This series contains color photographs and other materials from two recent exhibitions of Equi's work, Votive Candy and Cinema Taro. It also contains broadsides for events related to their work.
  - Exhibitions: Votive Candy and Cinema Tarot, 2008-2009 (Box 3, Folder 21-26)
  - Broadsides (Box 27)